{
  "reference_number": "10244",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Any means possible. Sorry, I will have to leave this for the scientific experts in the area to determine. If that includes foreign reductions\n\n included, so be it. Just whatever will work fastest & best."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If it's possible to do it by 2030, then do it. By that I mean, if it's possible to do this earlier rather than later, lets do this. We are already\n 2 decades behind the ball."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes - but only if the subsequent change is to speed up the process. Any attempt to slow or derail the process should be punishable\n\n with death (just jokes)."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - only if it's to make our target emission reductions & time frame more ambitious."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Work with every sector of society. If what we do adversely affects those in most need, then we need to nail down other areas that will\n\nlessen the affects on these people. NO sector shall be excluded, not the least the transport & agriculture sectors on some false\nequivalency claim that they're providing NZ with the means to be a modern economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Or option D, a mixture of advisory role & policy direction leading? Not sure. If I could TRUST a conservative government to do anything\nright I'd say this is the Govts role. But considering I have zero trust in these people to do anything that is in the public or\n\nenvironmental good, then I'd be skeptical of giving these roles to Govt. But of course, then we are giving a lot of power to a small\ngroup of officials... Good question."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If no, why undergo this exercise if we are only going to cover one half of the issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Hiding behind 'commercial sensitivity' is a cop-out. There's a reason why Tragedy of the Commons should be compulsory in schools\n\nagain, we are all in this together, not some 'special' exclusions."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Ever since I was a spotty Geography student at Linwood High School in ChCh in the mid 1980s, doing my research project of particle\n\nemissions in ChCh's infamous winter smog, the problems of pollution & it's adverse affect on humanity & the environment, it's been\npretty bloody evident that we need change. Going on to do a Geography degree at Canty Uni, studying under some of NZ's most\npreeminent scholars in the area of Climate Change & human impact on the environment, the clear message in the late 1980s was\n\nwe were already too late to save us from ourselves. Honestly, 40 years later, that we are still having this 'debate' it beggars belief. But\nthen after nearly a decade of belittling science & academics (re the disgusting personal attacks on the likes of Dr Mike Joy), I can see\n\nhow we are at this point. We need RADICAL change. In my humble, but educated opinion, we are too late to the party, but better late\nthan never. Whatever we can do to make this process faster (yet scientifically rigorous), the better. I'm in awe of places like University\n\nof British Columbia, where I am fortunate to have lived 5x since 1999, which has these goals already in place (some time ago). Some\nsay, so what, a University can do it. When the University year is underway, including the retirement homes, condos, student\n\naccommodation & daily staff & students on site, UBC has an on site population of 110,000 people, or the same size roughly of\nDunedin. Does Dunedin have a ZERO emissions plan in place... We are well behind the ball on this one. But in order to combat the\ninevitable big money back-lash, fronted by idiot conservative sock puppets, we must have a public education programme to\n\naccompany this. When I was a teacher, I included the Tragedy of the Commons in all my units of teaching, this is an increasingly rare\nfeat these days. Civics education, with concepts of Te Triti & Tragedy of the Commons must be core to this. The general public must\n\nbe educated on this, they need to be able to buy into what they are doing & shown the benefits of it. In short, we are 30-40 years\nbehind the ball, do this, do it properly & do it now, but hurry up would ya? Many thanks.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
